<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc docName="draft-openconfig-netmod-model-catalog-00" ipr="trust200902" category="info">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="YANG Model Catalog">Catalog and registry for YANG models</title>
    <author initials="K." surname="D'Souza" fullname="Kevin D'Souza">
      <organization>AT&amp;T</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>200 S. Laurel Ave</street>
          <city>Middletown</city>
          <region>NJ</region>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>kd6913@att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Shaikh" fullname="Anees Shaikh">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Pkwy</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94043</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>aashaikh@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <!-- Include Rob Shakir as author -->
    <?rfc include="http://rob.sh/files/ietf-author.xml"?>
    <date month="October" year="2015" />

    <area>Operations and Management</area>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document presents an approach for a YANG model catalog and registry
        that allows users to find models relevant to their use cases from the
        large and growing number of YANG modules being published.  The model
        catalog may also be used to define bundles of YANG modules required to
        realize a particular service or function.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
      <t>
        As <xref target="RFC6020">YANG</xref> adoption and usage grows, the
        number of YANG models (and corresponding module and submodule files)
        published is increasing rapidly. This growing collection of modules
        potentially enables a large set of management use cases, but from a
        user perspective, it is a daunting task to navigate the largely ad-hoc
        landscape of models to determine their functionality, availability,
        and implementations.  For example, the <xref target="RTG-AD-YANG">IETF
        Routing Area Coordination page</xref> currently tracks nearly 150 YANG
        models related to layer 2 and layer 3 technologies.
      </t>
      <t>
        YANG models are also being developed and published beyond the
        IETF, for example by open source projects, other standards
        organizations, and industry forums.  These efforts are
        generally independent from each other and often result in
        overlapping models.  While we recognize that models may come
        from multiple sources, the current approach of having a flat
        online listing of models is not sufficient to help users find
        the models they need, along with the information to retrieve
        and utilize the models in actual operational systems.  There
        is a need for a wider registry and catalog of available models
        that provides a central reference for model consumers and
        developers.
      </t>
      <t>
        The idea of a model catalog is inspired by service catalogs
        in traditional IT environments.  Service catalogs serve as
        software-based registries of available services with
        information needed to discover and invoke them.
      </t>
      <t>
        In <xref target="I-D.openconfig-netmod-model-structure">earlier
        proposals</xref> we motivated the need for a common structure that
        allows a set of models to be used together coherently in order to
        manage, for example, a complete network device.  Other efforts have
        subsequently proposed further options for modeling the complete <xref
        target="I-D.rtgyangdt-rtgwg-device-model">device structure</xref>.  We
        also briefly described the notion of a model catalog to provide a
        structured view of all of the models available from different
        organizations. In this document, we further elaborate on some of the
        details and use cases for a model catalog and registry.
      </t>
      <t>
        There are recent proposals that address related issues in terms of
        understanding the set of YANG models available on a device <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-netconf-yang-library" />, and how to classify models
        based on their role in describing a multi-layer service <xref
        target="I-D.bogdanovic-netmod-yang-model-classification" />.  The
        latter, in particular, describes a taxonomy for classifying YANG
        models that could also be used in the model catalog, though it does
        not address the problem of classifying model functionality, which is a
        key requirement.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title = "Model catalog and registry requirements" anchor="reqs">
      <t>
        At a high level, the model catalog must provide enough information for
        users to determine which models are available to describe a specific
        service or technology, and attributes of those models that would help
        the user select the best model for their scenario.  While this draft
        does not specifically address selection criteria -- they would be
        specific to each user -- some examples include:
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            model maturity, including availability of server implementations
            (e.g., native device support)
          </t>
          <t>
            available of co-requisite models, and complexity of the model
            dependencies
          </t>
          <t>
            identity and reputation of the entity or organization publishing
            the model
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        The model catalog should, therefore, include key information about YANG
        modules, including:
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              organization responsible for publishing and maintaining the
              module with contact information; organizations may include
              standards bodies (SDOs), industry forums, open source projects,
              individuals, etc.
            </t>
            <t>
              classification of the module or model, which could be along several axes,
              e.g., functional category, service vs. element models,
              commercial vs. free-to-use, etc.
            </t>
            <t>
              for open models, the license under which the model is distributed; this
              is important if there are limitations on how the model may be modified
              or redistributed
            </t>
            <t>
              module dependencies, e.g., a list of all of the YANG modules that
              are required
            </t>
            <t>
              pointer to the YANG module, e.g., a URI that can be machine-processed
            </t>
            <t>
              implementation information, for example, a list of
              available server implementations that support the module
            </t>
            <t>
              authentication information to allow users to verify that
              the model they retrieve is authentic and unaltered
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Establishing a globally applicable classification scheme for models
          is not straightforward -- each organization developing models likely
          has its own taxonomy or organization strategy for YANG modules.
          This is an area of the catalog that is likely to require
          extensibility and customization, e.g., by letting each organization
          augment the schema with its own categories.  Similarly, users may
          want to define their own classifications for use by internal
          systems.
        </t>
        <t>
          The proposed catalog schema should be useful as a local database,
          deployed by a single user, and also as a global registry that can be
          used to discover available models.  For example, the local catalog
          could be used to define the approved set of models for use within an
          organization, while the registry serves as a channel for all model
          developers to make information about their models available.  The
          <xref target="RFC3688">IETF XML Registry</xref>, maintained by IANA
          serves a similar purpose for XML documents used in IETF protocols,
          but it is limited to IETF-defined YANG models, is tied to XML
          encoded data, and has a very limited schema.
        </t>
        <t>
          The registry implementation could be as simple as a metadata database that
          reflects the proposed catalog schema, along with means for online access
          and viewing.  A key requirement for the online registry would be a robust
          query capability that allows users to search for modules meeting a
          variety of selection criteria, along with an easy way to retrieve modules
          (where applicable).
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Model catalog schema" anchor="catalog">
        <t>
          We propose a schema for the model catalog defined using YANG (see the modules
          in <xref target="models" />).  The YANG modules in the catalog are
          organized at the top level by the publishing organization and its associated
          contact information.  The catalog structure is shown below.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork>
    +--rw organizations
      +--rw organization* [name]
         +--rw name       string
         +--rw type?      identityref
         +--rw contact?   string
         +--rw modules
            +--rw module* [name]
               +--rw name                string
               +--rw namespace?          string
               +--rw prefix?             string
               +--rw revision?           string
               +--rw summary?            string
               +--rw module-version?     string
               +--rw module-hierarchy
               |     ...
               +--rw classification
               |     ...
               +--rw dependencies
               |     ...
               +--rw module-usage
               |     ...
               +--rw implementations
                     ...
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          In this model, each organization publishes a list of available
          modules, each module having associated data describing its
          classification, dependencies, usage information, and implementation
          information.  In addition, some of the basic module metadata is
          included in the catalog, e.g., namespace, prefix, and revision.
        </t>
        <section title="Module information" anchor="module">
          <t>
            Each module has several types of information associated with it.
            These are described below.
          </t>
          <t>
            The basic information includes module metadata as mentioned above
            and also the location of module in its own dependency chain.  The
            module-hierarchy container indicates whether the module is a
            submodule of another module, and has a reference to its parent
            module.
          </t>
          <t>
            The classification data is meant to capture some base information
            but leave the taxonomy largely to model publishers.  The category
            and subcategory leaves are identities that are expected to be
            augmented with additional values.  The classification also includes
            a status to indicate the development or deployment status of the
            module, e.g.,  whether it is purely experimental, or mature
            enough for production use.  The classification data is shown
            below:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
        +--rw module* [name]
               +--rw classification
                  +--rw status?        identityref
                  +--rw category?      identityref
                  +--rw subcategory?   identityref
            </artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            In this initial version of the catalog schema, the module
            dependencies are represented as a simple list of references
            to co-requisite modules.  The model assumes that required
            modules are also represented in the catalog, and that only the
            first-level dependencies are included in the list.  That is, each
            of the listed modules can be examined to determine its dependencies.
          </t>
          <t>
            The usage data contains information required to retrieve and
            validate the module.  Specifically, it includes authentication
            and validation data to ensure the origin and integrity of the
            module, respectively.  The authentication information will be
            further developed in future revisions of the document; in the current
            version, these can be considered placeholders.  This section also
            includes a URI for modules that can be downloaded directly.  This
            part of the schema is shown below:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
        +--rw module* [name]
           +--rw module-usage
              +--rw authentication?   string
              +--rw md5-hash?         string
              +--rw access-uri?       inet:uri
            </artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The implementation container provides information about known
            implementations of the module, for example by network devices or
            other servers.  This data is structured as a list to account for
            multiple implementations of a module, e.g., by different vendors.
            It includes some basic information about the platform on which the
            module is supported, and the status of the implementation, but it
            is expected that details and limitations of the implementation will
            require consulting the implementor.  The implementation information
            in the catalog is shown below:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
        +--rw module* [name]
           +--rw implementations
              +--rw implementation* [implementation-id]
                 +--rw implementation-id        string
                 +--rw description?             string
                 +--rw reference?               union
                 +--rw implementor-name?        string
                 +--rw platform?                string
                 +--rw platform-version?        string
                 +--rw implementation-status?   identityref
            </artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Module composition with bundles" anchor="services">
        <t>
          From an operational perspective, the utility of a single module is
          quite limited.  Most, if not all, use cases require multiple
          modules that work together coherently.  Managing a network device
          typically requires configuration and operational state models for
          device-wide services, network protocols, virtual instances, etc.
          Network services, such as those delivered by many service providers,
          require not only infrastructure-level management models, such as devices
          and protocols, but also service-level models that describe service parameters.
        </t>
        <t>
          The model catalog and registry provides a common way to define
          service bundles, or recipes, that describe the set of modules required
          for realizing the feature or service.  For example, a Layer 3 VPN bundle would
          list its required configuration and state models, including
          VRFs, interfaces, BGP, policy, ACLs, and QoS.  Similar
          bundles can be defined for other services or use
          cases, for example, basic Internet operations such as adding
          new peers or customers, or setting up Layer 2 VPNs.  Note
          these bundle definitions complement actual
          configuration models for such services, which may focus on
          providing an abstracted set of configuration or operational
          state variables.  These variables would then be mapped onto device level
          variables.  We leave discussion of such mapping mechanisms
          to future revisions.
        </t>
        <t>
          Bundle definitions are particularly useful for organizations that identify
          and validate a set of models that are used to build a service, and then
          define an approved bundle based on that set.  Users within the organization
          can be assured that the corresponding bundles are known to work together
          to support the desired service.  Another use case for bundle definitions is
          for third-party testing or certification organizations to provide services to
          validate a set of modules and maintain the bundle.
        </t>
        <section title="Schema for module bundles" anchor="recipe">
          <t>
            We propose an initial YANG-defined schema for describing a service
            bundle for building composite services and functions (shown below).
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
    +--rw bundle
      +--rw name?          string
      +--rw version?       string
      +--rw description?   string
      +--rw category?      string
      +--rw subcategory?   string
      +--rw modules
         +--rw module* [module-type]
            +--rw module-type             string
            +--rw catalog-reference? -> /cat:organizations/.../module/name
            +--rw application-sequence?   uint8
            </artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            Each bundle includes basic information such as the name of the
            feature or service, the bundle version, and its category and
            subcategory.  The modules comprising the bundle are contained in
            the modules list with a reference to the module in the catalog.
            The application sequence number can be used to indicate an
            ordering of the modules in realizing the service, for example,
            device or element configuration modules followed by service
            configuration models.  The application sequence is a high level
            indication; a complete realization of the service would require a
            detailed definition of the mapping between module variables at
            different levels as discussed in <xref target="services" />.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">

      <t>
        The model catalog and registry described in this document do not define actual
        configuration and state data, hence are not directly responsible for
        security risks.
      </t>
      <t>
        However, since the model catalog is intended to be an authoritative
        and authenticated database of published modules, there are security
        considerations in securing the catalog (both contents and access), and
        also in authenticating organizations that deposit data into the catalog.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        The YANG model catalog is intended to complement the IANA XML
        Registry.  YANG modules defined in this document may be entered
        in the XML registry if they are placed or redirected for
        the standards track, with an appropriate namespace URI.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="YANG modules" anchor="models">

      <t>The model catalog and associated types modules are listed below.
      </t>
	     <figure>
	       <artwork><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file openconfig-module-catalog.yang
<?yfile include="file:///tmp/openconfig-module-catalog.yang"?>
<CODE ENDS>
 ]]>
        </artwork>
        </figure>
      <figure>
         <artwork><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file openconfig-catalog-types.yang
<?yfile include="file:///tmp/openconfig-catalog-types.yang"?>
<CODE ENDS>
 ]]>
        </artwork>
        </figure>
      <t>
        The feature bundle module is listed below.
      </t>
        <figure>
         <artwork><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file openconfig-feature-bundle.yang
<?yfile include="file:///tmp/openconfig-feature-bundle.yang"?>
<CODE ENDS>
 ]]>
        </artwork>
        </figure>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative references">
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6020.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3688.xml"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative references">
      <reference anchor="RTG-AD-YANG" target="http://trac.tools.ietf.org/area/rtg/trac/wiki/RtgYangCoordSummary">
        <front>
          <title>Routing Area Yang Coordinator's Summary Page</title>
          <author initials="Q." surname="Wu" fullname="Qin Wu">
            <organization>Huawei</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="D." surname="Sinicrope" fullname="David Sinicrope">
            <organization>Ericsson</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2015" />
        </front>
      </reference>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.openconfig-netmod-model-structure"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.rtgyangdt-rtgwg-device-model"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netconf-yang-library"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.bogdanovic-netmod-yang-model-classification"?>
    </references>
<!--
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
        The authors are grateful for valuable contributions to this document and
        the associated models from: Chris Chase, Luyuan Fang, and Jim Uttaro.
      </t>
    </section>
-->
  </back>
</rfc>
