<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc docName="draft-shaikh-rtgwg-policy-model-00" ipr="trust200902" category="info">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Routing Policy Model">Routing Policy Configuration Model for Service Provider Networks</title>
    <author initials="A." surname="Shaikh" fullname="Anees Shaikh">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Pkwy</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94043</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>aashaikh@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials = 'R.' surname='Shakir' fullname='Rob Shakir'>
      <organization abbrev='BT'>BT</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>pp. C3L, BT Centre</street>
          <street>81, Newgate Street</street>
          <city>London</city>
          <code>EC1A 7AJ</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <email>rob.shakir@bt.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.bt.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="K." surname="D'Souza" fullname="Kevin D'Souza">
      <organization>AT&amp;T</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>200 S. Laurel Ave</street>
          <city>Middletown</city>
          <region>NJ</region>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>kd6913@att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="C." surname="Chase" fullname="Chris Chase">
      <organization>AT&amp;T</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>9505 Arboretum Blvd</street>
          <city>Austin</city>
          <region>TX</region>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>chase@labs.att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
<!--
    <author initials="J." surname="Uttaro" fullname="James Uttaro">
      <organization>AT&amp;T</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>200 S. Laurel Avenue</street>
          <city>Middletown</city>
          <region>NJ</region>
        </postal>
	     <email>ju1738@att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="C." surname="Chase" fullname="Chris Chase">
      <organization>AT&amp;T</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>9505 Arboretum Blvd</street>
          <city>Austin</city>
          <region>TX</region>
        </postal>
	<email>chase@labs.att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Bansal" fullname="Deepak Bansal">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>205 108th Ave. NE, Suite 400</street>
          <city>Bellevue</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>dbansal@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
-->      
    <date month="January" year="2015" />

    <area>Routing</area>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines a YANG data model for configuring and
        managing routing policies in a vendor-neutral way and based on
        actual operational practice.  The model provides a generic policy
        framework which can be augmented with protocol-specific policy
        configuration. 
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
      <t>This document describes a <xref target="RFC6020">YANG</xref>
      data model for routing policy configuration based on operational
      usage and best practices in a variety of service provider
      networks.  The model is intended to be vendor-neutral, in order
      to allow operators to manage policy configuration in a
      consistent, intuitive way in heterogeneous
      environments with routers supplied by multiple vendors.
      </t>
      <section title = "Goals and approach" anchor="goals">
      <t>
      This model does not aim to be feature complete -- it is a
      subset of the policy configuration parameters available
      in a variety of vendor implementations, but supports widely
      used constructs for managing how routes are imported,
      exported, and modified across different routing protocols.
      The model development approach has been to examine actual
      policy configurations in use across a number of operator
      networks.  Hence the focus is on enabling policy configuration
      capabilities and structure that are in wide use.
      </t>

      <t>
      Despite the differences in details of policy expressions and
      conventions in various vendor implementations, the model
      reflects the observation that a relatively simple condition-
      action approach can be readily mapped to several existing vendor
      implementations, and also gives operators an intuitive and
      straightforward way to express policy without sacrificing
      flexibility.  A side affect of this design decision is that
      legacy methods for expressing policies are not considered.  Such
      methods could be added as an augmentation to the model if
      needed.
      </t>

     <t>
      Consistent with the goal to produce a data model that is vendor
      neutral, only policy expressions that are deemed to be widely
      available in existing major implementations are included in the
      model.  Those configuration items that are only available from
      a single implementation are omitted from the model with the
      expectation they will be available in separate vendor-provided
      modules that augment the current model.
      </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Model overview" anchor="overview">
      <t>
      The routing policy model is defined in two YANG modules, the
      main policy module, and an auxiliary module providing
      additional generic types.  The model has three main parts:
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
          A generic framework to express policies as sets of related
          conditions and actions. This includes match sets and actions
          that are useful across many routing protocols.
          </t>
          <t>
          A structure that allows routing protocol models to add
          protocol-specific policy conditions and actions though
          YANG augmentations.  There is a complete example of this
          for <xref target="RFC4271">BGP</xref> policies in the proposed vendor-neutral
          <xref target="BGP-Model">BGP data model</xref>.
          </t>
          <t>
          A reusable grouping for attaching import and export rules in
          the context of routing configuration for different
          protocols, VRFs, etc.  This also enables creation of policy
          chains and expressing default policy behavior.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        These modules make use of the standard Internet types,
        such as IP addresses, autonomous system numbers, etc.,
        defined in <xref target="RFC6991">RFC 6991</xref>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Route policy expression" anchor="expression">
      <t>
      Policies are expressed as a sequence of top-level policy 
      definitions each of which consists of a sequence of policy statements.
      Policy statements in turn consist of simple condition-action
      tuples. Conditions may include mutiple match or comparison
      operations, and similarly, actions may effect multiple changes to
      route attributes, or indicate a final disposition of accepting
      or rejecting the route.  This structure is shown below.
      </t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>
   +--rw routing-policy
      +--rw policy-definition* [name]
         +--rw name         string
         +--rw statement* [name]
            +--rw name          string
            +--rw conditions!
            |     ...
            +--rw actions!
                  ...
        </artwork>
      </figure>

      <section title="Policy conditions" anchor="conditions">
        <t>
        Policy statements consist of a set of conditions and actions
        (either of which may be empty).  Conditions are used to
        match route attributes against a defined set (e.g., a prefix
        set), or to compare attributes against a specific value.
        </t>

        <t>
        Match conditions may be further modified using the
        match-set-options configuration which allows operators to
        change the behavior of a match.  Three options are supported:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>ALL - match is true only if the given value matches
              all members of the set.
            </t>
            <t>ANY - match is true if the given value matches any
              member of the set.
            </t>
            <t>INVERT - match is true if the given value does not
              match any member of the given set.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
        Comparison conditions may similarly use options to change how
	      route attributes should be tested, e.g., for equality or
	      inequality, against a given value.
        </t>

        <t>
        While most policy conditions will be added by individual
        routing protocol models via augmentation, this routing policy
        model includes several generic match conditions and also the
        ability to test which protocol or mechanism installed a route
        (e.g., BGP, IGP, static, etc.).  The conditions included in
        the model are shown below.
        </t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
    +--rw routing-policy
      +--rw policy-definition* [name]
        +--rw statement* [name]
          +--rw conditions!
            +--rw call-policy?        -> /routing-policy/...
            +--rw match-prefix-set?   -> /routing-policy/...
            +--rw match-neighbor-set? -> /routing-policy/...
            +--rw match-tag-set?      -> /routing-policy/...
            +--rw match-set-options?     pt:match-set-options-type
            +--rw install-protocol-eq?   identityref
            +--rw igp-conditions
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Policy actions" anchor="actions">

        <t>
        When policy conditions are satisfied, policy actions are used
        to set various attributes of the route being processed, or to
        indicate the final disposition of the route, i.e., accept or
        reject.
        </t>

        <t>
        Similar to policy conditions, the routing policy model includes
        generic actions in addition to the basic route
        disposition actions.  These are shown below.
        </t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
    +--rw routing-policy
      +--rw policy-definition* [name]
         +--rw statement* [name]
            +--rw actions!
              +--rw accept-route?   empty
              +--rw reject-route?   empty
              +--rw igp-actions
                +--rw set-tag?   pt:tag-type
          </artwork>
        </figure>

      </section>

      <section title="Policy subroutines" anchor="subroutines">

        <t> 
        Policy 'subroutines' (or nested policies) are
        supported by allowing policy statement conditions to reference
        other policy definitions using the call-policy configuration.
        Called policies apply their conditions and
        actions before returning to the calling policy statement and
        resuming evaluation.  The outcome of the called policy affects
        the evaluation of the calling policy.  If the called policy
        results in an accept-route (either explicit or by default),
        then the subroutine returns an effective boolean true value to
        the calling policy.  For the calling policy, this is equivalent
        to a condition statement evaluating to a true value and
        evaluation of the policy continues
        (see <xref target="evaluation"></xref>).  Note that
        the called policy may also modify attributes of the route in
        its action statements. Similarly, a reject-route action
        returns false and the calling policy evaluation will be
        affected accordingly.
        </t>

      	<t>
      	Note that the called policy may itself call other policies (subject
      	to implementation limitations).  The model does not prescribe a
        nesting depth because this varies among implementations, with
        some major implementations only supporting a single subroutine,
        for example.  As with any routing policy construction, care
        must be taken with nested policies to ensure that the effective
        return value results in the intended behavior.  Nested policies
        are a convenience in many routing policy constructions but
        creating policies nested beyond a small number of levels (e.g., 2-3)
        should be discouraged.
        </t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Policy evaluation" anchor="evaluation">

      <t>
      Evaluation of each policy definition proceeds by evaluating its
      corresponding individual policy statements in order.  When a
      condition statement in a policy statement is satisfied, the
      corresponding action statement is executed.  If the action
      statement has either accept-route or reject-route actions,
      evaluation of the current policy definition stops, and no further
      policy definitions in the chain are evaluated.
      </t>

      <t>
      If the condition is not satisfied, then evaluation proceeds to
      the next policy statement.  If none of the policy statement
      conditions are satisfied, then evaluation of the current policy
      definition stops, and the next policy definition in the chain is
      evaluated.  When the end of the policy chain is reached, the
      default route disposition action is performed (i.e., reject-route
      unless an an alternate default action is specified for the
      chain).
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Applying routing policy" anchor="usage">

      <t>
      Routing policy is applied by defining and attaching policy chains
      in various routing contexts.  Policy chains are sequences of
      policy definitions (described in <xref target="expression">
      </xref>) that have an associated direction (import or export)
      with respect to the routing context in which they are defined.
      The routing policy model defines an apply-policy grouping that
      can be imported and used by other models.  As shown below, it
      allows definition of import and export policy chains, as well as
      specifying the default route disposition to be used when no
      policy definition in the chain results in a final decision.
      </t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>
     +--rw apply-policy
        +--rw import-policies*  -> /rpol:routing-policy/...
        +--rw default-import-policy?   default-policy-type
        +--rw export-policies*  -> /rpol:routing-policy/...
        +--rw default-export-policy?   default-policy-type
        </artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>
      The default policy defined by the model is to reject the route for
      both import and export policies.
      </t>

      <t>
      An example of using the apply-policy group in another routing
      model is shown below for BGP.  Here, import and export policies
      are applied in the context of a particular BGP peer group.  Note
      that the policy chains reference policy definitions by name that
      are defined in the routing policy model.
      </t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>
     +--rw peer-group* [group-name]
        |  +--rw group-name                string
        |  +--ro bgp-group-common-state
        |  +--rw description?              string
        |  +--rw graceful-restart!
        |  |  +--rw restart-time?        uint16
        |  |  +--rw stale-routes-time?   decimal64
        |  +--rw apply-policy
        |  |  +--rw import-policies*  -> /rpol:routing-policy/...
        |  |  +--rw default-import-policy?   default-policy-type
        |  |  +--rw export-policies*  -> /rpol:routing-policy/...
        |  |  +--rw default-export-policy?   default-policy-type
        ...
        </artwork>
      </figure>


    </section>

    <section title="Routing protocol-specific policies" anchor="augment">

      <t>
      Routing models that require the ability to apply routing policy
      may augment the routing policy model with protocol or other
      specific policy configuration.  The routing policy model
      assumes that additional defined sets, conditions, and actions
      may all be added by other models.
      </t>

      <t>
      An example of this is shown below, in which the BGP configuration
      model in <xref target="BGP-Model"></xref>
      adds new defined sets to match on community values or AS paths.
      The model similarly augments BGP-specific conditions and actions
      into the corresponding sections of the routing policy model.
      </t>


      <figure>
        <artwork>
+--rw routing-policy
      +--rw defined-sets!
      |  +--rw prefix-set* [prefix-set-name]
      |  |  +--rw prefix-set-name    string
      |  |  +--rw prefix* [address masklength masklength-range]
      |  |     +--rw address             inet:ip-address
      |  |     +--rw masklength          uint8
      |  |     +--rw masklength-range    string
      |  +--rw neighbor-set* [neighbor-set-name]
      |  |  +--rw neighbor-set-name    string
      |  |  +--rw neighbor* [address]
      |  |     +--rw address    inet:ip-address
      |  +--rw tag-set* [tag-set-name]
      |  |  +--rw tag-set-name    string
      |  |  +--rw tag* [value]
      |  |     +--rw value    pt:tag-type
      |  +--rw bgp-pol:bgp-defined-sets
      |     +--rw bgp-pol:community-set* [community-set-name]
      |     |  +--rw bgp-pol:community-set-name    string
      |     |  +--rw bgp-pol:community-members*    union
      |     +--rw bgp-pol:ext-community-set* [ext-community-set-name]
      |     |  +--rw bgp-pol:ext-community-set-name    string
      |     |  +--rw bgp-pol:ext-community-members*    union
      |     +--rw bgp-pol:as-path-set* [as-path-set-name]
      |        +--rw bgp-pol:as-path-set-name       string
      |        +--rw bgp-pol:as-path-set-members*   string
        </artwork>
      </figure>

    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      
      <t>Routing policy configuration has a significant impact on network operations,
      and as such any related model carries potential security risks.
      </t>

      <t>YANG data models are generally designed to be used with the
      NETCONF protocol over an SSH transport.  This provides an
      authenticated and secure channel over which to transfer
      configuration and operational data.  Note that use of
      alternate transport or data encoding (e.g., JSON over HTTPS)
      would require similar mechanisms for authenticating and
      securing access to configuration data.
      </t>

      <t>Most of the data elements in the policy model could be
      considered sensitive from a security standpoint.  Unauthorized
      access or invalid data could cause major disruption.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>This YANG data model and the component modules currently use
      a temporary ad-hoc namespace.  If and when it is placed on redirected for
      the standards track, an appropriate namespace URI will be
      registered in the <xref target="RFC3688">IETF XML Registry"</xref>.
      The routing policy YANG modules will be registered in the
      "YANG Module Names" registry [RFC6020].
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="YANG modules" anchor="models">

      <t>The routing policy model is described by the YANG modules in the
      sections below.
      </t>
    
      <section title="Routing policy model">
	<figure>
	<artwork><![CDATA[	
<CODE BEGINS> file routing-policy.yang
<?rfc include="routing-policy"?>
<CODE ENDS>
 ]]>
        </artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Routing policy types">
	     <figure>
	     <artwork><![CDATA[	
<CODE BEGINS> file policy-types.yang
<?rfc include="policy-types"?>
<CODE ENDS>
 ]]>
	     </artwork>
	     </figure>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Policy examples" anchor="examples">

      <t>
      Below we show an example of XML-encoded configuration data using
      the routing policy and BGP models to illustrate both how policies
      are defined, and also how they can be applied.
      </t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[	
<?rfc include="routing-policy-example.xml"?>
 ]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative references">
      <reference anchor="RFC6020">
        <front>
          <title>YANG - A Data Modeling Language for
            the Network Configuration Protocol (NETCONF)</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Bjorklund" fullname="Martin
            Bjorklund">
            <organization>Tail-f Systems</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2014" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6020" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC4271">
      	<front>
      	  <title>A Border Gateway Protocol 4 (BGP-4)</title>
      	  <author initials="Y." surname="Rekhter" fullname="Yakov Rekhter">
      	    <organization/>
      	  </author>
      	  <author initials="T." surname="Li" fullname="Tony Li">
      	    <organization/>
      	  </author>
      	  <author initials="S." surname="Hares" fullname="Susan Hares">
      	    <organization/>
      	  </author>
      	  <date year="2006" month="January"/>
      	</front>
      	<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4271"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC6991">
        <front>
          <title>Common YANG Data Types</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Schoenwaelder" fullname="Juergen Schoenwaelder">
            <organization>Jacobs University</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="July" year="2013" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6991" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC3688">
        <front>
          <title>The IETF XML Registry</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Mealling" fullname="Michael
	    Mealling">
            <organization>Verisign, Inc.</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="January" year="2004" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3688" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative references">
      <reference anchor="BGP-Model" target="https://github.com/YangModels/yang/tree/master/experimental/openconfig/bgp">
        <front>
          <title>BGP Configuration Model for Service Provider
            Networks</title>
          <author></author>
          <date month="January" year="2015" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors are grateful for valuable contributions to this
      document and the associated models from: Jim Uttaro, Josh George,
      Vijay Gill, Ina Minei, Steve
      Padgett, Ebben Aires, Eric Osborne, Luyuan Fang,
      Carl Moberg, Stephane Litkowski, and Russ White.
      </t>
<!--
 other folks who have provided feedback: Carl Moberg (Cisco), Keyur Patel (Cisco), Jeff Haas (Juniper), Adam Simpson (ALU)
-->
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
