<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc docName="draft-openconfig-rtgwg-local-routing-00" ipr="trust200902" category="info">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Local Routing Model">A Data Model for Locally Generated Routes in Service Provider Networks</title>
    <author initials="A." surname="Shaikh" fullname="Anees Shaikh">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Pkwy</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94043</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>aashaikh@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="J." surname="George" fullname="Joshua George">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Pkwy</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94043</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jgeorge@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <!-- Include Rob Shakir as author -->
    <?rfc include="http://rob.sh/files/ietf-author.xml"?>
    <author initials="F." surname="Chen" fullname="Feihong Chen">
      <organization>Verizon Communications</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>40 Sylvan Rd.</street>
          <city>Waltham</city>
          <region>MA</region>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>feihong.x.chen@verizon.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="July" year="2015" />

    <area>Routing</area>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines a YANG data model for configuring and
        managing locally generated routes in a vendor-neutral way and
        based on operational best practice.  Locally generated routes
        are those created by configuration, rather than by dynamic
        routing protocols.  Such routes include static routes, locally
        created aggregate routes for reducing the number of constituent
        routes that must be advertised, summary routes for IGPs, etc.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
      <t>
      This document describes a simple <xref target="RFC6020">YANG</xref>
      data model for locally generated routes, i.e., those not created by
      dynamic routing protocols.  These include static routes, locally
      created aggregate routes, summary routes for IGPs, etc.
      </t>
        <section title = "Goals and approach" anchor="goals">
        <t>
        This model expresses locally generated routes as generically as
        possible, avoiding configuration of protocol-specific attributes
        at the time of route creation.  This is primarily to avoid
        assumptions about how underlying router implementations handle
        route attributes in various routing table data structures they
        maintain.  Hence, the definition of locally generated routes
        essentially creates 'bare' routes that do not have any protocol-
        specific attributes.
        </t>
        <t>
        When protocol-specific attributes must be attached to a route
        (e.g., communities on a locally defined route meant to be
        advertised via BGP), the attributes should be attached via a
        protocol-specific policy after importing the route into the
        protocol for distribution (again via routing policy).  This
        model is intended to be used with the generic routing policy
        framework defined in <xref target="I-D.shaikh-rtgwg-policy-model"
        />.
        </t>
        <t>
        This model does not aim to be feature complete -- it is a
        subset of the configuration parameters available in a variety
        of vendor implementations, but supports widely
        used constructs for managing local routes.  Model development
        has been primarily driven by examination of actual configurations
        across operator networks.
        </t>
        <t>
        While this document provides an overview of the model, the
        most current and authoritative version is available in the
        public <xref target="YANG-REPO">YANG model repository</xref>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Model overview" anchor="overview">
      <t>
      In this initial version of the local routing model, two primary
      types of locally generated routes are supported, static routes
      and local aggregates. Static routes are manually configured routes
      with a defined prefix and next-hop.  The model support next-hops
      specified as an IP address, interface, or a special defined value,
      e.g., DISCARD to prevent forwarding for the specified prefix.
      Aggregate routes are used to summarize constituent routes and
      avoid having to advertise each constituent individually, and hence
      increase routing table size.  Aggregate routes are not used for
      forwarding, rather they are "activated" when a constituent route
      with a valid next hop is present in the IP routing table.
      </t>
      <t>
      The model structure is shown below:
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork>
    +--rw local-routes
      +--rw config
      +--ro state
      +--rw static-routes
      |  +--rw static* [prefix]
      |        ...
      +--rw local-aggregates
         +--rw aggregate* [prefix]
               ...
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
      Note that the model follows the convention of representing
      configuration and operational state at the leaves of the
      tree, based on recommendations in <xref target="I-D.openconfig-netmod-opstate" />.
      In this case, the operational state consists primarily of the applied
      configuration.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Interaction with routing policy" anchor="policy">
      <t>
      In many vendor implementations, local routes may be annotated with
      various route attributes or policies.  For example, when creating
      a locally generated aggregate route, it is often possible to specify
      <xref target="RFC4271">BGP</xref> communities which can then be
      used when filtering the routes
      sent to particular neighbors or peer groups.  IGP implementations
      such as IS-IS and OSPF have similar capability to create "summary"
      routes that serve a similar purpose to BGP aggregates.
      </t>
      <t>
      Since these and other local routes are conceptually similar from
      an operator standpoint, there is a desire to create a single
      model that may be used generically to address a number of use cases.
      The approach taken in this model is to define locally generated
      routes as "bare" routes, i.e., without any protocol-specific attributes
      such as BGP communities, IGP tags, etc.  Instead, these attributes are
      expected to be added via policy when locally generated routes are
      injected into a particular protocol for subsequent advertisement.
      </t>
      <t>
      Another important motivation for not including protocol-specific
      attributes when configuring local routes is that it assumes
      implementations can support the association of a variety of attributes
      with a route.  While this may be true in some implementations, others
      may segregate routing tables for different protocols into different
      data structures such that it would not be possible to attach attributes
      from, say BGP, onto an OSPF route.  For this reason, we constrain
      attributes on locally generated routes to be attached via policy as
      they are imported into different protocols.
      </t>
      <t>
      For example, consider the case of configuring a new prefix to be
      advertised to neighbors via BGP.  Using the local routing model
      and the routing policy model in <xref target="I-D.shaikh-rtgwg-policy-model"
      />, one way to do this is enumerated below:
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            Declare a static route for the advertised prefix using
            the local routing model (e.g., with a next hop set to DISCARD).
            This route is placed in the IP routing table.
          </t>
          <t>
            Define a policy to add BGP attributes to the route -- the
            policy would match on the prefix and the origin of the route
            (i.e., STATIC) and its action could be to add a BGP
            community.
          </t>
          <t>
            Apply the BGP policy as an import policy within BGP, e.g.,
            using the apply-policy statement in the policy model, to
            import the route into BGP.
          </t>
          <t>
            Export the route to neighbors using an export policy as
            usual, filtering on the added community attribute if appropriate.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        The step of creating a policy to add BGP (or other
        protocol-specific) attributes to the route is optional
        if an operator simply wishes to export the route to neighbors,
        as opposed to also filtering on attributes that are assumed to
        be present on the locally generated route.
      </t>
      <t>
        This version of the model does support the capability to specify
        a generic route tag that can be associated with locally generated
        routes (i.e., both statics and aggregates).  The tag can be used
        to filter routes that are imported into different routing protocols,
        for example, or to control which routes are exported to a neighbor.
        The route tagging capability may be refined further as more
        implementor feedback is incorporated into the model.
      </t>
      </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">

      <t>Routing configuration has a significant impact on network operations,
      and as such any related model carries potential security risks.
      </t>

      <t>YANG data models are generally designed to be used with the
      NETCONF protocol over an SSH transport.  This provides an
      authenticated and secure channel over which to transfer
      configuration and operational data.  Note that use of
      alternate transport or data encoding (e.g., JSON over HTTPS)
      would require similar mechanisms for authenticating and
      securing access to configuration data.
      </t>

      <t>Most of the data elements in the local routing model could be
      considered sensitive from a security standpoint.  Unauthorized
      access or invalid data could cause major disruption.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>This YANG data model and the component modules currently use
      a temporary ad-hoc namespace.  If and when it is placed on redirected for
      the standards track, an appropriate namespace URI will be
      registered in the <xref target="RFC3688">IETF XML Registry"</xref>.
      The routing policy YANG modules will be registered in the
      "YANG Module Names" registry [RFC6020].
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="YANG module" anchor="models">

      <t>The local routing model is described by the YANG module below.
      </t>

	<figure>
	<artwork><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file local-routing.yang
<?yfile include="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/YangModels/yang/master/experimental/openconfig/local-routing/local-routing.yang"?>
<CODE ENDS>
 ]]>
        </artwork>
        </figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Examples" anchor="examples">

      <t>
      Below we show an example of XML-encoded configuration data using
      the local routing model, in conjunction with the policy <xref
      target="I-D.shaikh-rtgwg-policy-model" /> and BGP <xref
      target="I-D.shaikh-idr-bgp-model" /> models to illustrate how local
      aggregate routes are defined and distributed into protocols.  Although
      the example focuses on BGP, the aggregate routes may be used with other
      routing protocols (e.g., IGPs) as mentioned in Section
      <xref target="policy" />.  Note that
      the XML has been modified to improve readability.
      </t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
<?yfile include="file:///tmp/local-routing-example.xml"?>
 ]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative references">
      <reference anchor="RFC6020">
        <front>
          <title>YANG - A Data Modeling Language for
            the Network Configuration Protocol (NETCONF)</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Bjorklund" fullname="Martin
            Bjorklund">
            <organization>Tail-f Systems</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2014" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6020" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC4271">
      	<front>
      	  <title>A Border Gateway Protocol 4 (BGP-4)</title>
      	  <author initials="Y." surname="Rekhter" fullname="Yakov Rekhter">
      	    <organization/>
      	  </author>
      	  <author initials="T." surname="Li" fullname="Tony Li">
      	    <organization/>
      	  </author>
      	  <author initials="S." surname="Hares" fullname="Susan Hares">
      	    <organization/>
      	  </author>
      	  <date year="2006" month="January"/>
      	</front>
      	<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4271"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3688">
        <front>
          <title>The IETF XML Registry</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Mealling" fullname="Michael
	    Mealling">
            <organization>Verisign, Inc.</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="January" year="2004" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3688" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative references">
      <reference anchor="YANG-REPO" target="https://github.com/YangModels/yang/tree/master/experimental/openconfig/local-routing">
        <front>
          <title>A Data Model for Locally Generated Routes in Service Provider Networks</title>
          <author></author>
          <date month="July" year="2015" />
        </front>
      </reference>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.shaikh-rtgwg-policy-model.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.openconfig-netmod-opstate.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.shaikh-idr-bgp-model.xml"?>
    </references>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors are grateful for valuable contributions to this
      document and the associated models from: Phil Bedard, Kevin Brintnall,
      Matt John, Marcus Hines, and Eric Osborne.
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
